<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://www.fda.gov/oc/datacouncil/stylesheets/spl/spl.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><document xmlns="urn:hl7-org:v3" xmlns:voc="http://www.hl7.org/v3/voc" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:hl7-org:v3 http://www.fda.gov/oc/datacouncil/schemas/spl/spl.xsd">
<id root="FD191C06-9D3B-4E46-9F79-90F6AF614947" />
<code code="34391-3" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="HUMAN PRESCRIPTION DRUG LABELING" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">Metronidazole Injection USP<br />METRONIDAZOLE<br />500 mg/Container (5 mg/mL)</title>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<setId root="FD191C06-9D3B-4E46-9F79-90F6AF614947" />
<versionNumber value="1" />
<author>
<time />
<assignedEntity>
<representedOrganization>
<name>B. Braun Medical, Inc.</name>
</representedOrganization>
</assignedEntity>
</author>
<component>
<structuredBody>
<component>
<section>
<id root="9B72F633-E2C2-79AD-E54F-69F153761CC9" />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<subject>
<manufacturedProduct>
<manufacturedMedicine>
<code code="0264-5535" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.69" />
<name>Metronidazole</name>
<formCode code="C42946" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="INJECTION" />
<activeIngredient>
<quantity>
<numerator unit="mg" value="500">
<translation code="C28253" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLIGRAM" value="500" />
</numerator>
<denominator unit="mL" value="100">
<translation code="C28254" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLILITER" value="100" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<activeIngredientSubstance>
<code code="140QMO216E" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.4.9" codeSystemName="FDA SRS" />
<name>Metronidazole</name>
<activeMoiety>
<activeMoiety>
<code code="140QMO216E" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.4.9" codeSystemName="FDA SRS" />
<name>Metronidazole</name>
</activeMoiety>
</activeMoiety>
</activeIngredientSubstance>
</activeIngredient>
<asEntityWithGeneric>
<genericMedicine>
<name>Metronidazole</name>
</genericMedicine>
</asEntityWithGeneric>
<inactiveIngredient>
<quantity>
<numerator unit="mg" value="740">
<translation code="C28253" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLIGRAM" value="740" />
</numerator>
<denominator unit="mL" value="100">
<translation code="C28254" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLILITER" value="100" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<inactiveIngredientSubstance>
<code code="451W47IQ8X" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.4.9" codeSystemName="FDA SRS" />
<name>Sodium Chloride</name>
</inactiveIngredientSubstance>
</inactiveIngredient>
<inactiveIngredient>
<quantity>
<numerator unit="mg" value="112">
<translation code="C28253" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLIGRAM" value="112" />
</numerator>
<denominator unit="mL" value="100">
<translation code="C28254" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLILITER" value="100" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<inactiveIngredientSubstance>
<code code="GR686LBA74" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.4.9" codeSystemName="FDA SRS" />
<name>Dibasic Sodium Phosphate</name>
</inactiveIngredientSubstance>
</inactiveIngredient>
<inactiveIngredient>
<quantity>
<numerator unit="mg" value="40">
<translation code="C28253" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLIGRAM" value="40" />
</numerator>
<denominator unit="mL" value="100">
<translation code="C28254" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLILITER" value="100" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<inactiveIngredientSubstance>
<name>Citric Acid Anhydrous</name>
</inactiveIngredientSubstance>
</inactiveIngredient>
<inactiveIngredient>
<inactiveIngredientSubstance>
<name>Water</name>
</inactiveIngredientSubstance>
</inactiveIngredient>
<asContent>
<quantity>
<numerator unit="mL" value="100">
<translation code="C28254" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="MILLILITER" value="100" />
</numerator>
<denominator value="1">
<translation value="1" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<containerPackagedMedicine>
<code />
<formCode code="C43167" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="BAG" />
<asContent>
<quantity>
<numerator value="24">
<translation code="C48474" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="BAG" value="24" />
</numerator>
<denominator value="1">
<translation value="1" />
</denominator>
</quantity>
<containerPackagedMedicine>
<code code="0264-5535-32" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.69" />
<formCode code="C43184" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="CASE" />
</containerPackagedMedicine>
</asContent>
</containerPackagedMedicine>
</asContent>
</manufacturedMedicine>
<consumedIn>
<substanceAdministration>
<routeCode code="C38276" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.3.26.1.1" displayName="INTRAVENOUS" />
</substanceAdministration>
</consumedIn>
</manufacturedProduct>
</subject>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="AF42A34A-A08E-DED0-6AD8-0DD1E75C5D9E" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml" />
<text><paragraph><content styleCode="bold">Sterile</content></paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold">For Intravenous Infusion Only.</content></paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="8BABF2D5-67C4-A605-0DCE-232E57F49824" />
<code code="34066-1" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="BOXED WARNING SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">WARNING</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole has been shown to be carcinogenic in mice and rats (see <content styleCode="bold"><linkHtml href="#Precautions">PRECAUTIONS</linkHtml></content>). Its use, therefore, should be reserved for serious anaerobic infections where, in the judgment of the physician, the benefit outweighs the possible risk.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="D1A0AB05-E083-C47C-2E77-EF8ECAAF8F93" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml" />
<text><paragraph>To reduce the development of drug-resistant bacteria and maintain the effectiveness of Metronidazole Injection USP and other antibacterial drugs, Metronidazole Injection USP should be used only to treat or prevent infections  that are proven or strongly suspected to be caused by bacteria.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="C74E7175-6608-9D1F-8934-F9ED414B7F80" />
<code code="34089-3" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="DESCRIPTION SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">DESCRIPTION</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP, sterile, is a parenteral dosage form of a synthetic antibacterial agent, 2-methyl-5-nitroimidazole-1-ethanol:</paragraph><renderMultiMedia referencedObject="MM1" /><paragraph>Each 100 mL of Metronidazole Injection USP contains a sterile, nonpyrogenic, isotonic, buffered solution of Metronidazole USP 500 mg, Sodium Chloride USP 740 mg, Dibasic Sodium Phosphate&#8226;7H<sub>2</sub>O USP 112 mg, and Citric Acid Anhydrous USP 40 mg in Water for Injection USP. Metronidazole Injection USP has a calculated osmolarity of 297 mOsmol/liter and a pH of 5.8 (4.5&#8211;7.0). Sodium content: 13.5 mEq/container.</paragraph><paragraph>The <content styleCode="bold">PAB</content><sup>&#174;</sup> plastic container system is a copolymer of ethylene and propylene formulated and developed for parenteral drugs. The copolymer contains no plasticizers and exhibits virtually no leachability. The safety of the plastic container has been confirmed by biological evaluation procedures.</paragraph><paragraph>The material passes Class VI testing as specified in the U.S. Pharmacopeia for Biological Tests &#8211; Plastic Containers. These tests have shown that the container is nontoxic and biologically inert. The container-solution unit is a closed system and is not dependent upon entry of external air during administration. No overwrap is necessary.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<observationMedia ID="MM1">
<value mediaType="image/jpeg" xsi:type="ED"><reference value="metronidazole-image01.jpg" /></value>
</observationMedia>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="CD2D83FC-45D1-20BD-696D-4AEF888C2BE4" />
<code code="34090-1" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">CLINICAL PHARMACOLOGY</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole is a synthetic antibacterial compound. Disposition of metronidazole in the body is similar for both oral and intravenous dosage forms, with an average elimination half-life in healthy humans of eight hours.</paragraph><paragraph>The major route of elimination of metronidazole and its metabolites is via the urine (60&#8211;80% of the dose), with fecal excretion accounting for 6&#8211;15% of the dose. The metabolites that appear in the urine result primarily from side-chain oxidation [1-(<content styleCode="italics">&#946;</content>-hydroxyethyl)-2-hydroxymethyl-5-nitroimidazole and 2-methyl-5-nitroimidazole-1-yl-acetic acid] and glucuronide conjugation, with unchanged metronidazole accounting for approximately 20% of the total. Renal  clearance of metronidazole is approximately 10 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>.</paragraph><paragraph>Metronidazole is the major component appearing in the plasma, with lesser quantities of the 2-hydroxymethyl metabolite also being present. Less than 20% of the circulating metronidazole is bound to plasma proteins. Both the  parent compound and the metabolite possess <content styleCode="italics">in vitro</content> bactericidal activity against most strains of anaerobic bacteria.</paragraph><paragraph>Metronidazole appears in cerebrospinal fluid, saliva, and human milk in concentrations similar to those found in plasma. Bactericidal concentrations of metronidazole have also been detected in pus from hepatic abscesses.</paragraph><paragraph>Plasma concentrations of metronidazole are proportional to the administered dose. An eight-hour intravenous infusion of 100&#8211;4,000 mg of metronidazole in normal subjects showed a linear relationship between dose and peak plasma concentration.</paragraph><paragraph>In patients treated with a 0.5% intravenous solution of metronidazole using a dosage regimen of 15 mg/kg loading dose followed six hours later by 7.5 mg/kg every six hours, peak steady-state plasma concentrations of metronidazole averaged 25 mcg/mL with trough (minimum) concentrations averaging 18 mcg/mL.</paragraph><paragraph>Decreased renal function does not alter the single-dose pharmacokinetics of metronidazole. However, plasma clearance of metronidazole is decreased in patients with decreased liver function.</paragraph><paragraph>In one study newborn infants appeared to demonstrate diminished capacity to eliminate metronidazole. The elimination half-life, measured during the first three days of life, was inversely related to gestational age. In infants whose gestational ages were between 28 and 40 weeks, the corresponding elimination half-lives ranged from 109 to 22.5 hours.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="AF5F31D3-3DBA-4AFF-E1A4-FCE54D5CC9B7" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">MICROBIOLOGY</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole is active <content styleCode="italics">in vitro</content> against most obligate anaerobes, but does not appear to possess any clinically relevant activity against facultative anaerobes or obligate aerobes. Against susceptible organisms, metronidazole is generally bactericidal at concentrations equal to or slightly higher than the minimal inhibitory concentrations. Metronidazole has been shown to have <content styleCode="italics">in vitro</content> and clinical activity against the following organisms:</paragraph><paragraph>Anaerobic gram-negative bacilli, including:</paragraph><list><item><caption>&#160;</caption><content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species, including the <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides fragilis</content> group (<content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis, B. distasonis, B. ovatus, B. thetaiotaomicron, B. vulgatus</content>) <content styleCode="italics">Fusobacterium</content> species</item></list><paragraph>Anaerobic gram-positive bacilli, including:</paragraph><list><item><caption>&#160;</caption><content styleCode="italics">Clostridium</content> species and susceptible strains of <content styleCode="italics">Eubacterium</content></item></list><paragraph>Anaerobic gram-positive cocci, including:</paragraph><list><item><caption>&#160;</caption><content styleCode="italics">Peptococcus niger</content><br /><content styleCode="italics">Peptostreptococcus</content> species</item></list></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="A78B4E1D-BAC4-ECA9-A1B3-41DADA5FA1AB" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">SUSCEPTIBILITY TESTS</title>
<text><paragraph>Bacteriologic studies should be performed to determine the causative organisms and their susceptibility to metronidazole; however, the rapid, routine susceptibility testing of individual isolates of anaerobic bacteria is not always practical, and therapy may be started while awaiting these results.</paragraph><paragraph>Quantitative methods give the most accurate estimates of susceptibility to antibacterial drugs. A standardized agar dilution method and a broth microdilution method are recommended.<footnote>Proposed standard:  PSM-11 &#8212; Proposed Reference Dilution Procedure for Antimicrobic Susceptibility Testing of Anaerobic Bacteria, National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards, and Sutter,<content styleCode="italics"> et al.</content>: Collaborative Evaluation of a Proposed Reference Dilution Method of Susceptibility Testing of Anaerobic Bacteria, <content styleCode="bold">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 16:</content>495&#8211;502 (Oct.) 1979; and Tally, <content styleCode="italics">et al.</content>: <content styleCode="italics">In Vitro</content> Activity of Thienamycin, <content styleCode="bold">Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 14:</content>436&#8211;438 (Sept.) 1978.</footnote></paragraph><paragraph>Control strains are recommended for standardized susceptibility testing. Each time the test is performed, one or more of the following strains should be included: <content styleCode="italics">Clostridium perfringens</content> ATCC 13124, <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides fragilis</content> ATCC 25285, and <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides thetaiotaomicron</content> ATCC 29741. The mode metronidazole MICs for those three strains are reported to be 0.25, 0.25 and 0.5 mcg/mL, respectively.</paragraph><paragraph>A clinical laboratory test is considered under acceptable control if the results of the control strains are within one doubling dilution of the mode MICs reported for metronidazole.</paragraph><paragraph>A bacterial isolate may be considered susceptible if the MIC value for metronidazole is not more than 16 mcg/mL. An organism is considered "resistant" if the MIC is greater than 16 mcg/mL. A report of "resistant" from the laboratory indicates that the infecting organism is not likely to respond to therapy.</paragraph><paragraph /><paragraph /></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="E567BFB6-817F-9944-8E0E-B00B38BA93FB" />
<code code="34067-9" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="INDICATIONS &amp; USAGE SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">INDICATIONS AND USAGE</title>
<text><paragraph>To reduce the development of drug-resistant bacteria and maintain the effectiveness of Metronidazole Injection USP and other antibacterial drugs, Metronidazole Injection USP should be used only to treat or prevent infections that are proven or strongly suspected to be caused by susceptible bacteria. When culture and susceptibility information are available, they should be considered in selecting or modifying antibacterial therapy. In the absence of such data, local epidemiology and susceptibility patterns may contribute to the empiric selection of therapy.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="2D31E4EA-9CF2-DB0B-7805-50BE1C7ED849" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">TREATMENT OF ANAEROBIC INFECTIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP is indicated in the treatment of serious infections caused by susceptible anaerobic bacteria. Indicated surgical procedures should be performed in conjunction with Metronidazole Injection USP therapy. In a mixed aerobic and anaerobic infection, antibiotics appropriate for the treatment of the aerobic infection should be used in addition to Metronidazole Injection USP.</paragraph><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP is effective in <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides fragilis</content> infections resistant to clindamycin, chloramphenicol, and penicillin.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Intra-Abdominal Infections</content>, including peritonitis, intra-abdominal abscess, and liver abscess, caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group (<content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis, B. distasonis, B. ovatus, B. thetaiotaomicron, B. vulgatus</content>), <content styleCode="italics">Clostridium</content> species, <content styleCode="italics">Eubacterium</content> species, <content styleCode="italics">Peptostreptococcus</content> species, and <content styleCode="italics">Peptococcus niger</content>.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Skin and Skin Structure Infections </content> caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group, <content styleCode="italics">Clostridium</content> species, <content styleCode="italics">Peptococcus niger</content>, <content styleCode="italics">Peptostreptococcus</content> species, and <content styleCode="italics">Fusobacterium</content> species.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Gynecologic Infections</content>, including endometritis, endomyometritis, tuboovarian abscess, and post-surgical vaginal cuff infection, caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group, <content styleCode="italics">Clostridium</content> species, <content styleCode="italics">Peptococcus niger</content>, and <content styleCode="italics">Peptostreptococcus</content> species.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Bacterial Septicemia </content> caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group and <content styleCode="italics">Clostridium</content> species.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Bone and Joint Infections</content>, as adjunctive therapy, caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Central Nervous System (CNS) Infections</content>, including meningitis and brain abscess, caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Lower Respiratory Tract Infections</content>, including pneumonia, empyema, and lung abscess, caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">Endocarditis</content> caused by <content styleCode="italics">Bacteroides</content> species including the <content styleCode="italics">B. fragilis</content> group.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="BB53FF6A-F5BC-3DB1-8E7E-274AE3E84CBA" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">PROPHYLAXIS</title>
<text><paragraph>The prophylactic administration of Metronidazole Injection USP preoperatively, intraoperatively, and postoperatively may reduce the incidence of postoperative infection in patients undergoing elective colorectal surgery which is classified as contaminated or potentially contaminated.</paragraph><paragraph>Prophylactic use of Metronidazole Injection USP should be discontinued within 12 hours after surgery. If there are signs of infection, specimens for cultures should be obtained for the identification of the causative organism(s) so that appropriate therapy may be given (see <content styleCode="bold"><linkHtml href="#Dosage_And_Administration">DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION</linkHtml></content>).</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="C5DA9A46-9CD9-AC8F-4EC8-19AA24782CC0" />
<code code="34070-3" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="CONTRAINDICATIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">CONTRAINDICATIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP is contraindicated in patients with a prior history of hypersensitivity to metronidazole or other nitroimidazole derivatives.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="766DA552-1677-C9A4-E029-67DF0F3E0049" />
<code code="34071-1" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="WARNINGS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">WARNINGS</title>
<text />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="31761A90-27E7-D474-50DA-15573876E674" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">CONVULSIVE SEIZURES AND PERIPHERAL NEUROPATHY</title>
<text><paragraph>Convulsive seizures and peripheral neuropathy, the latter characterized mainly by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity, have been reported in patients treated with metronidazole. The appearance of abnormal neurologic signs demands the prompt evaluation of the benefit/risk ratio of the continuation of therapy.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section ID="Precautions">
<id root="69494F5D-EC93-1ABB-F98C-808282E9F520" />
<code code="42232-9" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="PRECAUTIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">PRECAUTIONS</title>
<text />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="94B8CEDE-154E-390B-C8AE-EEC044D3BAB8" />
<code code="34072-9" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="GENERAL PRECAUTIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">GENERAL</title>
<text><paragraph>Prescribing Metronidazole Injection USP in the absence of a proven or strongly suspected bacterial infection or a prophylactic indication is unlikely to provide benefit to the patient and increases the risk of the development of drug-resistant bacteria.</paragraph><paragraph>Patients with severe hepatic disease metabolize metronidazole slowly, with resultant accumulation of metronidazole and its metabolites in the plasma. Accordingly, for such patients, doses below those usually recommended  should be administered cautiously.</paragraph><paragraph>Administration of solutions containing sodium ions may result in sodium retention. Care should be taken when administering Metronidazole Injection USP to patients receiving corticosteroids or to patients predisposed to edema.</paragraph><paragraph>Known or previously unrecognized candidiasis may present more prominent symptoms during therapy with Metronidazole Injection USP and  requires treatment with a candicidal agent.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="9A9ED5DE-01FB-C640-8CF3-68F58C315957" />
<code code="34076-0" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="INFORMATION FOR PATIENTS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">INFORMATION FOR PATIENTS</title>
<text><paragraph>Patients should be counseled that antibacterial drugs including Metronidazole Injection USP should only be used to treat bacterial infections. They do not treat viral infections (<content styleCode="italics">e.g.</content>, the common cold). When Metronidazole Injection USP is prescribed to treat a bacterial infection, patients should be told that although it is common to feel better early in the course of therapy, the medication should be taken exactly as directed. Skipping doses or not completing the full course of therapy may (1) decrease the effectiveness of the immediate treatment and (2) increase the likelihood that bacteria will develop resistance and will not be treatable by  Metronidazole Injection USP or other antibacterial drugs in the future.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="2919B013-A2E7-49FB-2C2B-A828E51673D5" />
<code code="34075-2" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="LABORATORY TESTS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">LABORATORY TESTS</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole is a nitroimidazole, and Metronidazole Injection USP should be used with caution in patients with evidence of or history of blood dyscrasia. A mild leukopenia has been observed during metronidazole administration; however, no persistent hematologic abnormalities attributable to metronidazole have been observed in clinical studies. Total and differential leukocyte counts are recommended before and after therapy.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="BC95A8A5-1078-6076-64BA-02913711B7BD" />
<code code="34073-7" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="DRUG INTERACTIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">DRUG INTERACTIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole has been reported to potentiate the anticoagulant effect of warfarin and other oral coumarin anticoagulants, resulting in a prolongation of prothrombin time. This possible drug interaction should be considered when Metronidazole Injection USP is prescribed for patients on this type of anticoagulant therapy.</paragraph><paragraph>The simultaneous administration of drugs that induce microsomal liver enzymes, such as phenytoin or phenobarbital, may accelerate the elimination of metronidazole, resulting in reduced plasma levels; impaired clearance of phenytoin has also been reported.</paragraph><paragraph>The simultaneous administration of drugs that decrease microsomal liver enzyme activity, such as cimetidine, may prolong the half-life and decrease plasma clearance of metronidazole.</paragraph><paragraph>Alcoholic beverages should not be consumed during metronidazole therapy because abdominal cramps, nausea, vomiting, headaches, and flushing may occur.</paragraph><paragraph>Psychotic reactions have been reported in alcoholic patients who are using metronidazole and disulfiram concurrently. Metronidazole should not be given to patients who have taken disulfiram within the last two weeks.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="E27E6707-2FAA-981D-81B5-6C7126391FED" />
<code code="34074-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="DRUG &amp;OR LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">DRUG/LABORATORY TEST INTERACTIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole may interfere with certain types of determinations of serum chemistry values, such as aspartate aminotransferase (AST, SGOT), alanine aminotransferase (ALT, SGPT), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), triglycerides, and hexokinase glucose. Values of zero may be observed. All of the assays in which interference has been reported involve enzymatic coupling of the assay to oxidation-reduction of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD <renderMultiMedia referencedObject="MM2" /> NADH). Interference is due to the similarity in absorbance peaks of NADH (340 nm) and metronidazole (322 nm) at pH 7.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<observationMedia ID="MM2">
<value mediaType="image/jpeg" xsi:type="ED"><reference value="metronidazole-image02.jpg" /></value>
</observationMedia>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="531938D9-DD3C-9BC2-6859-B8468D94F63A" />
<code code="34083-6" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="CARCINOGENESIS &amp; MUTAGENESIS &amp; IMPAIRMENT OF FERTILITY SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">CARCINOGENESIS, MUTAGENESIS, IMPAIRMENT OF FERTILITY</title>
<text />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="482D202C-2858-8D01-F08F-58EA124A0B18" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">Tumorigenicity in Rodents</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole has shown evidence of carcinogenic activity in studies involving chronic, oral administration in mice and rats, but similar studies in the hamster gave negative results. Also, metronidazole has shown mutagenic activity in a number of <content styleCode="italics">in vitro</content> assay systems, but studies in mammals (<content styleCode="italics">in vivo</content>) failed to demonstrate a potential for genetic damage.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="F0CA717B-AB4A-A3AD-FA47-EF861F9D461D" />
<code code="42228-7" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="PREGNANCY" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">PREGNANCY</title>
<text />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="3D2E6CAB-3E14-4659-5CE4-382D42993A06" />
<code code="34077-8" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="TERATOGENIC EFFECTS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">Teratogenic Effects</title>
<text />
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="BC764382-8458-6426-2975-68D47A7232BC" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">Pregnancy Category B</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole crosses the placental barrier and enters the fetal circulation rapidly. Reproduction studies have been performed in rats at doses up to five times the human dose and have revealed no evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the fetus due to metronidazole. Metronidazole administered intraperitoneally to pregnant mice at approximately the human dose caused fetotoxicity; administered orally to pregnant mice, no fetotoxicity was observed. There are, however, no adequate and well-controlled studies in pregnant women. Because animal reproduction studies are not always predictive of human response, and because metronidazole is a carcinogen in rodents, this drug should be used during pregnancy only if clearly needed.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="BECA54A6-BD34-41F3-3ADD-2EF84E378E31" />
<code code="34080-2" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="NURSING MOTHERS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">NURSING MOTHERS</title>
<text><paragraph>Because of the potential for tumorigenicity shown for metronidazole in mouse and rat studies, a decision should be made whether to discontinue nursing or to discontinue the drug, taking into account the importance of the drug to the mother. Metronidazole is secreted in human milk in concentrations similar to those found in plasma.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="C50B9985-DE2E-9DFB-6689-914B20961C7D" />
<code code="34081-0" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="PEDIATRIC USE SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">PEDIATRIC USE</title>
<text><paragraph>Safety and effectiveness in children have not been established.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="FF6CF458-CA62-39C5-6207-4C4F8DEAC014" />
<code code="34084-4" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="ADVERSE REACTIONS SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">ADVERSE REACTIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>The two most serious adverse reactions reported in patients treated with metronidazole have been convulsive seizures and peripheral neuropathy, the latter characterized mainly by numbness or paresthesia of an extremity. Since persistent peripheral neuropathy has been reported in some patients receiving prolonged oral administration of metronidazole, patients should be observed carefully if neurologic symptoms occur and a prompt evaluation made of the benefit/risk ratio of the continuation of therapy.</paragraph><paragraph>The following reactions have also been reported during treatment with intravenous metronidazole:</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">GASTROINTESTINAL: </content> Nausea, vomiting, abdominal discomfort, diarrhea, and an unpleasant metallic taste.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">HEMATOPOIETIC: </content> Reversible neutropenia (leukopenia).</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">DERMATOLOGIC: </content> Erythematous rash and pruritus.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM: </content> Headache, dizziness, syncope, ataxia and confusion.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">LOCAL REACTIONS: </content> Thrombophlebitis after intravenous infusion. This reaction can be minimized or avoided by avoiding prolonged use of indwelling intravenous catheters.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">OTHER: </content> Fever. Instances of a darkened urine have also been reported, and this manifestation has been the subject of a special investigation. Although the pigment which is probably responsible for this phenomenon has not been positively identified, it is almost certainly a metabolite of metronidazole and seems to have no clinical significance.</paragraph><paragraph>The following adverse reactions have been reported during treatment with oral metronidazole:</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">GASTROINTESTINAL: </content> Nausea, sometimes accompanied by headache, anorexia, and occasionally vomiting, diarrhea, epigastric distress, abdominal cramping, and constipation.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">MOUTH: </content> A sharp, unpleasant metallic taste is not unusual. Furry tongue, glossitis, stomatitis have occurred; these may be associated with a sudden overgrowth of <content styleCode="italics">Candida</content> which may occur during effective therapy.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">HEMATOPOIETIC: </content> Reversible neutropenia (leukopenia); rarely, reversible thrombocytopenia.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">CARDIOVASCULAR: </content>Flattening of the T-wave may be seen in electrocardiographic tracings.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM: </content> Convulsive seizures, peripheral neuropathy, dizziness, vertigo, incoordination, ataxia, confusion, irritability, depression, weakness, and insomnia.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">HYPERSENSITIVITY: </content> Urticaria, erythematous rash, flushing, nasal congestion, dryness of mouth (or vagina or vulva), and fever.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">RENAL: </content> Dysuria, cystitis, polyuria, incontinence, a sense of pelvic pressure, and darkened urine.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold italics">OTHER: </content> Proliferation of <content styleCode="italics">Candida</content> in the vagina, dyspareunia, decrease of libido, proctitis, and fleeting joint pains sometimes resembling "serum sickness". If patients receiving metronidazole drink alcoholic beverages, they may experience abdominal distress, nausea, vomiting, flushing, or headache. A modification of the taste of alcoholic beverages has also been reported.</paragraph><paragraph>Crohn's disease patients are known to have an increased incidence of gastrointestinal and certain extraintestinal cancers. There have been some reports in the medical literature of breast and colon cancer in Crohn's disease patients who have been treated with metronidazole at high doses for extended periods of time. A cause and effect relationship has not been established. Crohn's disease is not an approved indication for Metronidazole Injection USP.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="CFB788EB-AC8F-0765-AF5D-0C6DAA1016BC" />
<code code="34088-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="OVERDOSAGE SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">OVERDOSAGE</title>
<text><paragraph>Use of dosages of metronidazole higher than those recommended has been reported. These include the use of 27 mg/kg three times a day for 20 days, and the use of 75 mg/kg as a single loading dose followed by 7.5 mg/kg  maintenance doses. No adverse reactions were reported in either of the two cases.</paragraph><paragraph>Single oral doses of metronidazole, up to 15 g, have been reported in suicide attempts and accidental overdoses. Symptoms reported include nausea, vomiting, and ataxia.</paragraph><paragraph>Oral metronidazole has been studied as a radiation sensitizer in the treatment of malignant tumors. Neurotoxic effects, including seizures and peripheral neuropathy, have been reported after 5 to 7 days of doses of 6 to 10.4 g every other day.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="4E201041-4FCE-338E-17F1-9C3EA5992D63" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">TREATMENT</title>
<text><paragraph>There is no specific antidote for overdose, therefore, management of the patient should consist of symptomatic and supportive therapy.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section ID="Dosage_And_Administration">
<id root="0874CB79-A036-24D8-357A-A7D3F2C73FF3" />
<code code="34068-7" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="DOSAGE &amp; ADMINISTRATION SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION</title>
<text><paragraph>In elderly patients the pharmacokinetics of metronidazole may be altered and therefore monitoring of serum levels may be necessary to adjust the metronidazole dosage accordingly.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<section>
<id root="A6D8AD90-A50D-7E73-2B34-1E90272A2397" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">TREATMENT OF ANAEROBIC INFECTIONS</title>
<text><paragraph>The recommended dosage schedule for adults is:</paragraph><table width="60%"><col align="left" width="33%" />
<col align="left" width="67%" />
<tbody>
<tr><td>Loading Dose</td><td>15 mg/kg infused over one hour<br />(approximately 1 g for a 70-kg adult).</td></tr>
<tr><td>Maintenance Dose</td><td>7.5 mg/kg infused over one hour every six hours<br />(approximately 500 mg for a 70-kg adult). The first maintenance dose should be instituted six hours following the initiation of the loading dose.</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table><paragraph>Parenteral therapy may be changed to oral metronidazole when conditions warrant, based upon the severity of the disease and the response of the patient to Metronidazole Injection USP treatment. The usual adult oral dosage is 7.5 mg/kg every six hours.</paragraph><paragraph>A maximum of 4 g should not be exceeded during a 24-hour period.</paragraph><paragraph>Patients with severe hepatic disease metabolize metronidazole slowly, with resultant accumulation of metronidazole and its metabolites in the plasma. Accordingly, for such patients, doses below those usually recommended  should be administered cautiously. Close monitoring of plasma metronidazole levels<footnote>Ralph ED, Kirby WMM: Bioassay of Metronidazole With Either Anaerobic or Aerobic Incubation, <content styleCode="bold">J. Infect. Dis. 132:</content>587&#8211;591 (Nov.) 1975, or Gulaid, <content styleCode="italics">et al.</content>: Determination of Metronidazole and its Major Metabolites in Biological Fluids by High Pressure Liquid Chromatography, <content styleCode="bold">Br. J. Clin. Pharmacol. 6:</content>430&#8211;432, 1978.</footnote> and toxicity is recommended.</paragraph><paragraph>In patients receiving metronidazole injection in whom gastric secretions are continuously removed by nasogastric aspiration, sufficient metronidazole may be removed in the aspirate to cause a reduction in serum levels.</paragraph><paragraph>The dose of Metronidazole Injection USP should not be specifically reduced in anuric patients since accumulated metabolites may be rapidly removed by dialysis.</paragraph><paragraph>The usual duration of therapy is 7 to 10 days; however, infections of the bone and joint, lower respiratory tract, and endocardium may require longer treatment.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="3805E622-6AB9-6366-BEA0-9135B98D0805" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">PROPHYLAXIS</title>
<text><paragraph>For surgical prophylactic use, to prevent postoperative infection in contaminated or potentially contaminated colorectal surgery, the recommended dosage schedule for adults is:</paragraph><list listType="ordered" styleCode="Littlealpha"><item>15 mg/kg infused over 30 to 60 minutes and completed approximately one hour before surgery, followed by:</item><item>7.5 mg/kg infused over 30 to 60 minutes at 6 and 12 hours after the initial dose.</item></list><paragraph>It is important that (1) administration of the initial preoperative dose be completed approximately one hour before surgery so that adequate drug levels are present in the serum and tissues at the time of initial incision, and (2) Metronidazole Injection USP be administered, if necessary, at 6-hour intervals to maintain effective drug levels. Prophylactic use of Metronidazole Injection USP should be limited to the day of surgery only, following the above guidelines.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold">Caution: Metronidazole Injection USP is to be administered by slow intravenous drip infusion only, either as a continuous or intermittent infusion. IV admixtures containing metronidazole and other drugs should be avoided. Additives should not be introduced into the Metronidazole Injection USP solution. If used with a primary intravenous fluid system, the primary solution should be discontinued during metronidazole infusion. DO NOT USE EQUIPMENT CONTAINING ALUMINUM (E.G., NEEDLES, CANNULAE, ETC.) THAT MAY CONTACT THE DRUG SOLUTION.</content></paragraph><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP is a ready-to-use isotonic solution. <content styleCode="bold">NO DILUTION OR BUFFERING IS REQUIRED.</content> Do not refrigerate. Each container of Metronidazole Injection USP contains 13.5 mEq of sodium.</paragraph><paragraph>Parenteral drug products should be inspected visually for particulate matter and discoloration prior to administration, whenever solution and container permit. Do not use if cloudy or precipitated or if the seals are not intact.</paragraph><paragraph>Use sterile equipment. It is recommended that the intravenous administration apparatus be replaced at least once every 24 hours.</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="74304A4A-1FA0-2F01-64F0-87F2CD5CBC6D" />
<code code="34069-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="HOW SUPPLIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">HOW SUPPLIED</title>
<text><paragraph>Metronidazole Injection USP, sterile, is supplied in 100 mL PAB<sup>&#174;</sup> plastic containers, each containing an isotonic, buffered solution of 500 mg metronidazole; individually packaged in boxes of 24.</paragraph><table width="50%"><col align="center" width="50%" />
<col align="center" width="25%" />
<col align="center" width="25%" />
<thead>
<tr><th>NDC</th><th>Cat. No.</th><th>Size</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Metronidazole Injection USP</td><td /><td /></tr>
<tr><td>0264-5535-32</td><td>D5353-5224</td><td>100 mL</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table><paragraph>Exposure of pharmaceutical products to heat should be minimized. Avoid excessive heat. Protect from freezing. It is recommended that the product be stored at room temperature (25&#176;C); however, brief exposure up to 40&#176;C  does not adversely affect the product.</paragraph><paragraph><content styleCode="bold">Protect from light until use.</content></paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="431C3F51-1DF3-7AA6-348E-D96A86FECCFF" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml" />
<text><paragraph>Rx only</paragraph><paragraph>Revised: January 2004</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="F2ED89DB-6010-44E2-F468-60EBDACC80A4" />
<code code="38056-8" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SUPPLEMENTAL PATIENT MATERIAL SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml">Directions for Use</title>
<text><paragraph>Aseptic technique is required.</paragraph><list><item><caption styleCode="bold">1.</caption><content styleCode="bold">Caution</content>&#8211; Before use, perform the following checks: 							<list><item><caption>(a)</caption>Read the label. Ensure solution is the one ordered and is within the expiration date.</item><item><caption>(b)</caption>Inspect the solution in good light for cloudiness, haze or particulate matter; check the container for leakage or damage. Any container which is suspect should not be used.</item></list></item></list><paragraph>Use only if solution is clear and container and seals are intact.</paragraph><paragraph>Single dose plastic container. Discard unused portion.</paragraph><paragraph>Consult Package Insert for complete product information.</paragraph><list><item><caption styleCode="bold">2.</caption><content styleCode="bold">Caution</content>&#8211; IV admixtures containing metronidazole and other drugs should be avoided. Additives should not be introduced into the Metronidazole Injection USP solution. If used with a primary intravenous fluid system, the primary solution should be discontinued during metronidazole infusion. Do not use equipment containing aluminum (<content styleCode="italics">e.g.</content>, needles, cannulae, etc.) that may contact the drug solution.<br /><br /></item><item><caption styleCode="bold">3.</caption><content styleCode="bold">To Attach Administration Set</content> Remove the set port closure. Hold the container below the set port and grasp cap between thumb and forefinger, then roll cap upward (see Figure A). Push the spike into and through the diaphragm of the port (see Figure B). Continue with <content styleCode="bold">Directions for Use</content> for the administration set. Suspend the container using the hole in the lower flap.<br /><br /><renderMultiMedia referencedObject="MM3" /><br /><br /></item></list></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
<component>
<observationMedia ID="MM3">
<value mediaType="image/jpeg" xsi:type="ED"><reference value="metronidazole-image03.jpg" /></value>
</observationMedia>
</component>
</section>
</component>
<component>
<section>
<id root="2685B62C-FCFD-7766-01DA-064A727B3F87" />
<code code="42229-5" codeSystem="2.16.840.1.113883.6.1" codeSystemName="LOINC" displayName="SPL UNCLASSIFIED SECTION" />
<title mediaType="text/x-hl7-title+xml" />
<text><paragraph><content styleCode="bold">B. Braun Medical Inc.</content><br />Irvine, CA USA 92614-5895</paragraph><paragraph>&#169;2004 B. Braun Medical Inc.</paragraph><paragraph>Y36-002-497</paragraph></text>
<effectiveTime value="20060419" />
</section>
</component>
</structuredBody>
</component>
</document>
